foreign it's
July 18 2023
and we're in our second discussion on
chapter eight
so
where would anyone like to begin or any
general remark on chapter eight
what I can say
something I I added a couple of
questions to the list at the very end on
box 8.1
but we can we can go through some other
stuff
first
if you want sounds good
um
all right let's let's look at
the first question
yes perhaps if I
put some background in of my
understanding so
um
so my understanding is we have uh
well I think if we go to there's Rafael
boyatch or bogach's paper
um
a tutorial on free energy uh
which starts off with looking at a
single neuron with an input
uh with an input distribution of a
particular mean and and variance
yeah and and he then builds that up uh
to the point where you've got a
multi-layer system with multiple nodes
and the uh the the synapses represent uh
means and variances
um
I think there's
we're not seriously suggesting that that
synapses actually represent particular
means and variances or whatever but I
think
there's the idea that collectively a
population of neurons is going to encode
uh
mean values and variances
um and position is is inverse variance
of course
so
uh I suppose my other frame of reference
is gaussian mixture models
where you've you know you've got
gaussian's
characterized by uh weights or amplitude
mean and and variance
uh
something going on to box 8.1 I'm
confused that there seems to be a way of
treating
a Precision of a
as a as a magnitude as an amplitude
um or changing that
changing the gaussian uh perhaps of
buying reducing the variance increase in
the Precision is is going to increase
the peak
to make it more
prominent
uh which seems a strange
way of doing things
um
yeah exactly so so for me
well precision and attention are not
synonyms
uh
and attention seems to be a
or something at the
neuromodulation time scale
as opposed to synapting weights
at a much slower time scale or
General influence with with usual
um
synaptic or some neurotransmitters
uh so
yeah it it doesn't make sense how uh
well a lot of
a lot of the uh of that box
your mute
um yeah Ollie or anyone do you want to
give it that or
okay
so here
the Precision
being described is the Precision to the
sensory input
and so equivalent to attention to
in the sense that um if the uh and
reflected by the a matrix
so if uh the incoming sensory data
are inferred to be accurate
then they will update the hidden state
more
if the sensory data incoming were not
um
believed to be accurate low Precision
low attention
then
their
um
then observations wouldn't update hidden
States
I don't think that that necessarily
refers to the
psychological concept of attention
but is your question
[Music]
about
well
um
yeah
in terms of significance you could have
something that was
that was more important
or more worthy of attention at a
particular time
even though it had less
but a belief was was held with less
precision
um
what would you mean more important like
more relevant for survival importance
more
more relevant
um
yeah I think I so I I say it as
from uh
a gaussian mixture model
point of view I suppose so you could
have
um
uh
but let's let's take I think I'll put in
the questions of if if you have if you
have two gaussians let's say you've got
a a single sense input uh of measuring
the wavelength of light
and you're presented with apples and
pairs
and so pairs cover a fairly narrow green
spread of the green
so you've got a very
a very sharp
low variance distribution there
and your apples spread right across red
to Green
but that your input your environment
might actually have
uh a lot more apples than than pears
so even if you're in the
in a uh
if you sense something that was within
the the pairs
area of the spectrum
it still might be more likely that that
you've had an apple
that's exactly the prior
like
and that that's um factorized away from
the attention to the sensory input
the D is coming into the s from the left
side and the attention to sensory input
is coming up from the bottom
so you're able to
attend to sensory input or not
but but it is very it is very I believe
useful to consider what happens here
um
in in terms of um the variational
estimation
where there's no action we're not
choosing which thing to look at yet
but still in this mapping
the the fruit identification region of
the brain
the rate code would represent the
posterior on Apple to pair
zero if it's an apple one if it's a pair
and then the variance would represent
the uh
the
Precision on the sensory input mapping
to it
such that a high precision
High Precision belief which is to say
low Precision on sensory input
would have high inertia
as a belief
I think that's accurate
I think it part of the part of the issue
is that um
Precision can be on any variable
like uncertainty could be on any
variable
so it has to be clarified
Precision on what
and this is on sense Precision on
sensory input
and I think a question that Sanjeev
answered in and perhaps the most recent
uh meeting
attention waiting
rescales the
um attention to different variables is
what dictates the influence that they
have on the overall free energy gradient
descent
if you have two variables
and they both are equally attended to
then the free energy is a 50 50
compromise
such that there's going to be a flat
manifold where one of them is getting
better by one point one's getting worse
by one point
whereas if you're attending to one of
them but 10 times more than the other so
it's 10 times more Precision on that
belief
then
each increment of free energy
minimization you'd be willing to accept
10 decrements on the other one
yeah
it's the attention blends
the the role of each parameter being
optimized on the overall scalar
gradient descent
yeah I yeah I've still got a bit of a
block on the
on that I'll go away and if I think
about that but I think what you said
just
leads naturally on to my other point so
I so as I see it as as you say the uh
that's that rebalancing of the attention
so if if you if we have a tension given
to
uh extra set of input
then you know you're sensing the outside
world you're treating that as important
if you then shift to
proprioceptive
uh
attention
then
that's
that's more likely to to lead or that
would lead to action or
that there's there's the whole thing
about sensory attenuation why why does
sensory attenuation happen is it a
random thing
well there's there's the splitting
across and there's the there's a a
neuroscientific model framework
and then there's also actual we're
trying to do some engineering stuff
here
but on the the neuroscience
well yeah generally
are we saying that there is some
oscillation
um
uh flip-flopping between
uh sense and effectively action
or is it just something that's happening
randomly that's that things will drift
and get to it an action phase
or sensory balance
yeah I think there's a lot of pieces
there
um so systems don't have to have sensory
attenuation
if having a constant
uh uh regime of attention
it is simply how the system is defined
uh by Fiat
or at some level of generative modeling
for some variable there may not be any
reason to to propose this cognitive
phenomena
um however
whether you look at isicating and visual
input
where we have like Precision High
Precision on the sensory input when
we're fixed
and then we pull off the gas when we
move so that we suppress input while the
visual field is very shifted and then re
re-engage so whether we think about like
the icicade attention to visual input or
if we think about
um the uh motor control example in box
8.1
which is exactly analogous it's just
interceptive instead of x terreceptive
where there's a suppression of sensory
input
to
um support action selection instead of
um belief updating
in both those cases
a kind of adaptive
emergent cybernetic pattern is this
oscillation of attention
to enable the benefits of um
High attention to sensory input
but then also be able to transiently
engage another mode where input to
sensory uh
uh data is lowered
so I think that just turns out to be
a solution
or an approach to navigate
the the the trade-offs because you
wouldn't want to just have high
attention or only low attention
so then
then the navigation solution oscillates
between them
so this is so we're saying that this is
just something that happens to be
found
in real grains or as fit into a model of
of real brains it's not something that
is inherent within active inference it's
not something that appears in the in the
discrete time
uh domain is it
um I I guess you could model sensory
attenuation in discrete time
but correct sensory attenuation is not
unnecessary part of active inference
agents so why is this useful because
this pattern helps us understand the
cognitive similarities between speaking
and listening where the bird song
example is a famous case of sensory
attenuation like you expect the song to
be playing so as long as it's playing
you listen and then when it goes away
then now you take action
and then while acting your Precision
decreases until you eventually see his
acting again so turn taking conversation
isaacades
um motor control with proprioceptive
the cognitive patterns can be identified
and those are accounts of complex
phenomena that are first principles and
don't appeal to reward or reinforcement
they appeal to some specific
computational phenomena
that Maps between
the neurobiology Loosely like you
brought up with a mean in the variance
and the statistical parameterization
and then that model generates um unique
explanations and predictions
and say oh well maybe this um dyskinesia
is a is a challenge of initiating
movement and this one's a challenge of
terminating movements
yeah yes and there's there's a time with
various mental illness as well isn't
there so schizophrenia
title with sensory generation
it kind of reminds me of the uh the work
by Adam saffron of Albus
because
friston and Carhartt Harris had this
Rebus paper relaxed beliefs under
psychedelics
and then there was like this other
proposal was like sevis strengthened
beliefs under psychedelics
and then Adam was like well it's kind of
just altered
oh that's really General but it's just
like
increasing the Precision on this one
right then decrease the Precision on
something else so
there's not just a Precision variable
it has to be a little bit more unpacked
with Precision on what beliefs
because we could talk about beliefs on
um since uh States about beliefs on
latent States believe some action
it's all belief updating it's all
Bayesian beliefs
and can you think is is there any
reference that I perhaps I should read
that um
might get me thinking about Precision in
a better way
maybe the bird song
um Kristen and frith bird song
example
I can also maybe with Sanji if we can
ask and and see his simulation seem very
amenable to it
yeah I think possibly because I've
I've got it fixed in my mind the idea of
synapses encoding variants
uh whereas as you say variance is
there's this variance uh much more
broadly
were in the concept of making inferences
uh posteriors
uh
that's where I don't really have a good
handle I think this is a you know
there's a barrier I have a barrier so
how do I get through the barrier
yeah that's kind of a hard like a topic
and
it just reminds me of the end of seven
um
here
like we call D the prior
but of course once you escape the most
trivial pedagogical generative model
then it makes more sense to be clear
this is a prior on hidden States
because you're also talking about a
prior or hyper prior on other variables
and also that was like kind of the
motivation for the generalized notation
notation
so that we could which was originally
called generalized subscript notation
because we wanted to be able to talk
about like a preference on preference or
a policy on preference or a prior on
preference
because when you're in the nested models
you have to clarify which
term you're talking about
okay yeah so I'm I'm pretty much happy
with the rest of the chapter it's it's
that it's just that one box that I need
to get around so yeah so like you said
the Birdsong thing so I've read that in
the past
that that makes sense but it's this
ambiguity I have around
the word Precision
um and how it
well that that one phrase of precision
and attention being synonyms
is that that I've got the block on me
let me try one one more angle on this so
we're sitting up and sitting down
example from the sensory attenuation so
let's just say that our proprioceptors
give us like 90 confident information
[Music]
um
when we're in that state but when we're
moving it gives us
um 50 50 so it's totally ambiguous but
then it's 19 90 10 once we're in the
seated or the standing
um state
so
we have a true
um
hidden state which is our actual posture
and then
um let's just say that we're getting
seated input because we're seated
but because of a cognitive decision now
we prefers standing input
um
now if the pragmatic value were scaled
super high
then you would take the policy to stand
up
because the pragmatic value would just
overwhelm everything else
however if the pragmatic value is not
scaled super high
then there's a little bit of like a
frustration
because
um
it's your preferred state
but not so preferred that it's
overwhelming the the belief updating
to be anchored closer to the um sitting
down
so you have kind of these two peaks you
could be getting you could be you know
drawing from this peak of observations
sitting down or you could be drawing
from the other Peak
um and then
um even if this even if the other Peak
is slightly higher
the optimization still
holds to the left side
and then like by increasing the variance
reduce your precision
then
the in the in that ambiguity from the
sensory input
then the preferred
State then you can select action
to stand up
and kind of it's like temporarily
flattening the landscape so that you can
make a move
without needing to
um want it more
yeah I think something you said at the
beginning that was
very
significant I think because I'm I'm
thinking when we're talking about
Precision it's Precision of beliefs of
sensory input
whereas
there's also Precision on
uh in states and
you know between priors and new input
uh it's that balance
see what else happens
okay lockableterra
Thomas part
um explains some of this like the the
historiosity of this
lockabletera was used
to uh describe
structured sequential activities in the
continuous time setting
okay learning
a functional s that plays the role of a
free energy
this could definitely be unpacked a
little
more
but it seems like this is a continuous
time
free energy based method
for gradients
based optimization of mean and variance
of the LaPlace approximation
well it seems like I could use a little
bit more context
I'm I'm right in thinking so so if if we
visualize a a normal distribution and
we're saying
we increase the Precision
uh you know we can think of that as the
shape the change of shape of the
distribution
uh so that the peak goes up
so it's it is
that that's the right way of of thinking
about it we're changing the shape of the
normal distribution
so hence
uh
increasing increasing the Precision so
reducing the variance is is the same
thing as increasing the the peak
at the at the mean value which is the
mode as well
yeah yeah
yes it sharpens it when it's more
attended to
and this is sort of like the two um
the two faces of the KL Divergence is
mean seeking versus mode seeking
and attention modulation
[Music]
um
influences which one of those it goes to
as well as where that optimizations
um starts in the landscape
because if it's too attentive if it's
too attentive to get out of a local
Optima
then it becomes functionally mode
seeking
because whichever mode it gets to
it'll just think okay I'm doing as well
as I can
because also LaPlace doesn't
um the gaussian has support everywhere
but a LaPlace is a downward facing
parabola
so it doesn't have infinite support
whereas so it's not exactly a gaussian
mixture model
and then the mode seeking
[Music]
um
it just tries to find whatever the
highest point is and then fit a gaussian
around it versus the mean seeking tries
to cover as much of the distribution
[Music]
and match the center of gravity
with the central tendency
so in the case of the sitting up and
standing standing um
like
you you're you're usually wanting to be
pretty precise about your body's
position so you're mode seeking you're
mode seeking you're locally you're
sitting down
then it's like the attention relaxes
that moves the kl to be more like mean
seeking
now it's like 50 50. 50 your prior half
the time you're standing half you're
seated and the sensory data are
ambiguous
and you prefer to be standing
so then that preference breaks the
symmetry
and then you can re-sharpen your
attention back when you're standing
so then the KL can have kind of this
like end to end
um reduction of diversions
and the only knob that you had to change
was the attention
now how to adaptively tune attention
that's a question
but that's why it's it's um interesting
conversion to Evolution that we see the
same like cyclic attention strategy in
the cicade and in the um
standing example
so we see that as a repeated
heuristic
and
umdp chapter 7 has largely superseded
the use of generalized lockabletera and
active inference
that's kind of interesting
because that's like saying the discrete
time has kind of taken over from The
Continuous time
yeah yeah
I've made the point before so a lot of
those sort of classic examples were
including the bird song in
the SPM 12.
um
is is based on the
SPM ADM
active Dynamic expectation maximization
model so that's that's all within the
continuous well this
continuous time frame
uh
concept as opposed to
pomdp
um
so it's it's like that's yeah it has
been superseded
because all of the com so much of the
conversation now is about bomdb
yeah
eventually we'll we'll have every model
annotated in literature so we can look
at like the trends and the um
which ones were used but suffice to say
lockableterra I don't see this coming up
recently
and continuous times are definitely not
as frequent as POS mdps
I mean Pi mdp only describes continuous
time
and it's just so much closer to the
setting of uh discrete time
explicit planning
counterfactuals uh reinforcement
learning reward like
the discrete time formalism is a lot
closer to it
okay I suppose yes more more useful for
sort of high level sort of cognitive
functioning as opposed to the basic
movement in an environment
but that's kind of the cool like
Internet of Things question like what if
you could have a you know a wing
um or like a water you know something
and then all that it was really like
endowed with
was heuristics around attention
modulation
maybe that only takes like two lines or
something
and then like with this heuristic ground
attention
then it can do like a in a continuous
time
um
sensory capacity
whereas you could TR you could train a
pomdp
and do all these big like Matrix
calculations I mean that that's sort of
the question where do these um different
models have difference
computational advantages or
explainability advantages
yeah okay thanks yeah oh yeah these are
great questions
also the uh
the recent model stream nine
it'll I'm just reloading it
with Aspen Paul
um here it is
he presents a computational the only
other time we've seen computational
complexity estimates was with uh
branching time active inference
okay
I thought this was super fascinating so
here's um
so classical octave
s-i sophisticated inference
time step 30 horizon or two Horizon DP
dynamic programming
um aif one is um
is just single timestep active
so 30 times step
sophistication
10 to the 68
complexity
cognitive complexity
and just like how I just found it really
interesting how
the sophisticated inference blow up is
so high
and and uh
he's using dynamic programming based
methods
to learn smooth
priors on preference
so I think there's a lot of difference
there's a lot of different little motifs
that might have
very effective performance in a certain
setting like in the setting of a camera
that moves
isocating and blinking bite
converge to being an Adaptive strategy
so finding out which
generative models and phenomena
parsimoniously describe these different
natural systems
might be very helpful for
them being able to compose them together
that understand okay where do we need
thank you Ali
talk to you later
where do we need different
[Music]
um
difference
models
I think I asked him like can you do like
the full can you do like this
approximation in this part of the nested
model in that one in this part and he
said yes
so you could even Implement two
different approximations for different
parts the same generative model I think
okay then generalize synchrony okay
here's
where the bird song comes back into play
bird hears the song there's no need to
generate it if the bird predicts a song
that is not heard it must start singing
learning here
it's uh described more in the paper I
assume that it is learning according to
this box
this leads to turn taking sometimes
phrase to seeing from the same hymn
sheet
um
yes uh it it is
and
therefore it's not really like a model
of improvisational communication
or necessarily even communication as
information transmission
they're literally just it's like there's
something that has to be carried and
they just like one of them carries it
until the other one picks up
so it's like it's a very basal
aspect of communication because the
model is really just trying to describe
to turn taking
to generate bird song requires a
reduction in the Precision of
predictions about the consequence of
action I'm not sure why that is
why couldn't you take action and also
increase your Precision about the
consequences of your actions
that'd kind of be like action
um I mean might even be connected to
something like OCD
where action
that that
um
action that
when you take it blurs your precision
is kind of like self-terminated
because eventually you'll just wobble
out of that behavioral attractor
whereas if there's a behavior
that is that is increasing your
precision
so you're attending more and more to the
sensory outcomes
that that action is seeking
then I feel like that action becomes
like Tighter and Tighter
um like in a tractor
but something like like um I mean even
though a lot of times different uh
neuropathologies and stuff come up I
think the reality is a lot of these are
really sophisticated
multi-level cognitive phenomena and so
it's just kind of pointing in that
direction but it's not really it's not
it's not that's the same thing
generalized synchrony
um
again seeing from the same hymn sheet
they have learned to share the same
narrative I think
if you consider the song to be a
narrative
and also open question is like how much
is it is already like baked in and then
it's being fine-tuned
versus it's not like they're starting
with two different singing Concepts and
then actually learning the whole thing
but just
okay then
uh
Hybrid models
single models that contain both
continuous and discrete variables
in this case the lower level is
continuous time
x x Prime x sub Prime the higher level
is
um discrete time past present and future
this is the same family of model that
Ryan Smith at all explored in live
stream 46
active inference does not contradict
folk psychology where the lower level is
the motor active inference and then the
higher levels the decision making active
inference
there's supposed to be an edge here
um
uh message passing
uh procedures exist
for graphs that have discrete and
continuous time
so they're kind of brought up separately
just because of uh pedagogy
but
ultimately it seems like there's no
issue with mixing
the uh
the the
mapping between discrete and continuous
time
happens by basically giving discrete
State spaces uh
integer values in some continuous space
State space
like
here
you could associate the coordinates
with the discrete location but then also
have it be a continuous space
so then you I guess can have the
discrete time model and the continuous
model in the same
State space
um being like kind of described in one
from the discrete side as zero one and
then in the continuous one from
continuous space from zero to one
okay this is a little bit of the um
this is an icicated model probably this
is a useful paper to look more into
um
16 neural populations
four locations and four time steps
one two three and four
but I don't know why they stay active I
don't know why they don't drop back down
well and here's what what's happening in
this is the person is being told to look
at the cross
then
a DOT is being shown at the top of the
screen
there's some 200 millisecond delay
that represents like visual processing
then they really they accelerate
here's their point of maximum speed
the accelerate and then decelerate and
fixate on the queue
where the cube was
and each of these four traces represents
beliefs
but again I'm not sure why
why it's not just like one comes up and
then it goes down the second comes up it
goes down
okay mixture models gaussian mixture
models like you brought up earlier
what do you think the relevances of the
gaussian mixture here
Neil
um
because there's reference to sort of
Delta functions here so precise
well totally precise
prize there
um
so I'm not sure
where the gaussian comes in other than
that bottom equation
the normal distribution
the priors on the mean and the variance
are precise so we're basically just
looking for a point estimate on mean and
a point estimate on variance
not looking to have a secondary
uncertainty about me and in a secondary
uncertainty about variance
that's the Delta part
and then I guess the I subscript is the
number of mixtures
and maybe different observations are
being allocated or learned
to
um
the difference
mixtures categories
so the optimal you know if you had two
if you had one mixture it would be the
same as a gaussian if you have three
mixtures then you'd be trying to
parameterize three different gaussians
with different means and variances
and then assigning each data point to
one of those mixtures
and then the question of which
um
which number of mixtures of groups
should you have
is approached through Bayesian model
reduction Bayesian information Criterion
eight one
Birth song
ocular motor condition reflex
smooth eye Pursuit psychosis illusion
cicades
auction observation attention hybrid
model self-organization
yeah interesting and kind of
very sparse and brief chapter
I feel like it is very short and just
barely touches on a few
pieces
but I guess provides information where
there's other
continuous time models
what do you think
yeah nice it was very good chat so
[Music]
um
what this this is this is more
where my interest lies as soon as you
might have guessed I want to continue a
Time side of things
um I just have that one difficulty
around the Box having accepted what's in
the box everything else follows
fine it's it's yeah
it all hangs together quite neatly
um
but yeah there's various things have
been said I need to go away and digest
I'm just just like you're saying a point
estimate on variance
um whereas I'm thinking of
perhaps and confusing and getting
estimates and variants confused you know
the biggest variants included in the
estimate
um right and we we
um
variance is like the mean on our
variance estimator
and and uh usually we don't go two
levels deep
like usually the the standard uh
deviation
there's not an SD on the SD
usually
that's just the point estimate on
mean and variance
and then
but then it's like but the variance of
the mean isn't that just the variance
how is the variance different different
than the Precision on the mean
yeah plus I I mean let's think about the
class you know the people are 10 feet
tall plus or minus five
so variance is five by virtue of the
actual variation in height
but the Precision on the mean if we
sampled a million creatures might be
very low
but we might have a very confident
estimate it's 10 plus or minus 5.
or we might have a very imprecise
estimate that it's 10 plus or minus 1.
and then in the variational gradient
descent scheme
attention relates all the variables so
that
the gradient descents
strikes a balance
but that just begets the question how
does the attention get trained
so that in a multivariate optimization
[Music]
variables are being traded off
appropriately
including situations where there's a
dynamic reallocation of of optimization
Focus
hmm
you know how how is how is the whole
system
well how are those parameters of the the
um the chaotic attractor tuned
so that it does
um it does follow
contain trajectories stable rather than
just going off and
disappearing down
getting stuck into into in one attractor
rather than another
yeah
yeah well for uh for a system to be able
to be uh to descend into an attractor
and to escape it kind of has to be
pushed on the edge of chaos
perhaps some dynamic or oscillatory
component
otherwise it just gets attracted towards
attracted to
but okay cool
thank you well tomorrow's the first math
learning group or or so
so people are welcome to come to Discord
if um if they want but otherwise
see you all next time
that's great thanks Michelle bye